(Transcribed by TurboScribe.ai. Go Unlimited to remove this message.) When I spoke to you last at Christmas,
I asked you all, whatever your religion, to
pray for me on the day of my
coronation, to pray that God would give me
wisdom and strength to carry out the promises
that I should then be making.
Throughout this memorable day, I have been uplifted
and sustained by the knowledge that your thoughts
and prayers were with me.
I have been aware all the time that
my peoples, spread far and wide throughout every
continent and ocean in the world, were united
to support me in the task to which
I have now been dedicated with such solemnity.
Many thousands of you came to London from
all parts of the commonwealth and empire to
join in the ceremony, but I have been
conscious too of the millions of others who
have shared in it by means of wireless
or television in their homes.
All of you, near or far, have been
united in one purpose.
It is hard for me to find words
in which to tell you of the strength
which this knowledge has given me.
The ceremonies you have seen today are ancient,
and some of their origins are veiled in
the mists of the past.
But their spirit and their meaning shine through
the ages, never perhaps more brightly than now.
I have in sincerity pledged myself to your
service, as so many of you are pledged
to mine.
Throughout all my life and with all my
heart, I shall strive to be worthy of
your trust.
In this resolve, I have my husband to
support me.
He shares all my ideals and all my
affection for you.
Then, although my experience is so short and
my task so new, I have in my
parents and grandparents an example which I can
follow with certainty and with confidence.
There is also this.
I have behind me not only the splendid
traditions and the annals of more than a
thousand years, but the living strength and majesty
of the commonwealth and empire, of societies old
and new, of lands and races different in
history and origins, but all by God's will
united in spirit and in aim.
Therefore, I am sure that this, my coronation,
is not the symbol of a power and
a splendor that are gone, but a declaration
of our hopes for the future, and for
the years I may, by God's grace and
mercy, be given to reign and serve you
as your queen.
I have been speaking of the vast regions
and varied peoples to whom I owe my
duty, but there has also sprung from our
island home a theme of social and political
thought, which constitutes our message to the world
and, through the changing generations, has found acceptance
both within and far beyond my realms.
Parliamentary institutions, with their free speech and respect
for the rights of minorities and the inspiration
of a broad tolerance in thought and its
expression, all this we conceive to be a
precious part of our way of life and
outlook.
During recent centuries, this message has been sustained
and invigorated by the immense contribution in language,
literature and action of the nations of our
commonwealth overseas.
It gives expression, as I pray it always
will, to living principles as sacred to the
crown and monarchy as to its many parliaments
and peoples.
I ask you now to cherish them and
practice them too.
Then we can go forward together in peace,
seeking justice and freedom for all men.
As this day draws to its close, I
know that my abiding memory of it will
be not only the solemnity and beauty of
the ceremony, but the inspiration of your loyalty
and affection.
I thank you all from a full heart.
God bless you all.